Finding Aid for Corydon L. Ford papers, 1841-1900
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Corydon L. Ford papers 1841-1900, 1873-1900
Ford, Corydon L. (Corydon La), 1813-1894.
2 linear feet
851249 Aa 2
Dr. Corydon L. Ford was a professor of anatomy and physiology at the University of Michigan Department of Medicine and Surgery (now the Medical School), He taught from 1854 to 1894. The collection contains reports on his faculty activities, scattered correspondence, lecture notes, syllabi, plates, and other papers relating largely to his work in the Medical School; also visual materials.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The provenance of the collection is not known
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Corydon La Ford was born August 29, 1813 on a farm in Lexington, New York. Paralysis in one leg made it impossible for him to continue farming and at the age of 17 he became a teacher with a view to eventually becoming a physician. He received his M.D. from Geneva Medical College in 1842, where he then taught anatomy from 1842 to 1848. In 1847 he was appointed demonstrator of Anatomy in the Medical Department of the University of Buffalo, and while holding this position he was also Professor of Anatomy in the Castleton Medical College, Vermont. In 1854 he accepted the position of professor of anatomy at the University of Michigan; in 1860, he was named professor of anatomy and physiology. He taught for more than forty years, serving as dean of the faculty 1879-1880.
Aside from teaching, Ford wrote several significant works including "Questions on Anatomy, Histology, and Physiology, for the Use of Students" (last ed. Ann Arbor, 1878), "Syllabus of Lectures on Odontology, Human and Comparative (1884), and "Questions on the Structure and Development of the Human Teeth" (1885). Dr. Ford was given an LL.D. from Michigan in 1881. He died April 14, 1894.
The Corydon L. Ford papers offer strong documentation of medical education and practice in the last half of the 19th century. The collection is arranged in three series: Teaching Records, Topical Files, and Miscellaneous.
Subjects:
Anatomy.; Ford, Corydon L. (Corydon La), 1813-1894.; Physicians--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Medicine and Surgery.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Anatomy.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Tombs and sepulchral monuments.; Ford, Corydon L. (Corydon La), 1813-1894.; Tombs and sepulchral monuments--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Prints.
- Teaching Records
  Teaching Records is composed of files relating to Ford's career as a teacher. Material in this series includes lists of lectures given by Ford, class lists and a list of all members of the first five classes of the University of Michigan medical school, and extensive lecture notes.
  - Anatomy and Physiology (Box 1)
  - Castleton Medical College Memoranda 1849 (Box 1)
  - Geneva Medical College
    - Class Lists 1845-1849 (Box 1)
    - Synopsis of Lectures (Box 1)
  - Long Island College Hospital Lecture 1877 (Box 1)
  - Physiological Notes for Dental Students (Box 1)
  - Questions in Anatomy (Box 1)
  - "Some Questions on Odontogeny," 1890 (Box 1)
  - University of Buffalo 1847 (Box 1)
  - University of Michigan
    - Lecture Notes (Box 1)
    - List of Lectures (Box 1)
    - "Questions on Anatomy -- For the Use of Students," 1873 (Box 1)
    - Regents Meeting 1891 (Box 1)
    - Series "H" Dentistry (Box 1)
    - Student Records 1861-1862, 4 volumes (Box 1)
  - Lecture Notes
    - Anatomy Topics (Box 1)
    - Notes on Lectures on Physiology 1867 (Box 1)
    - Lecture Notes, 10 volumes (Box 1)
    - Synopses of Lectures of Osteology (Box 1)
- Topical Files
  The Topical Files are primarily composed of notes related to various subjects of interest to Ford. This series also includes essays written by Ford on a variety of subjects and features an essay recommending against tobacco use.
  - Air and Health (Box 1)
  - Blood (Box 1)
  - Cartilage (Box 1)
  - Circulation (Box 1)
  - Comparative Osteology, etc. (Box 1)
  - Dental (Box 1)
  - Dental Matters (Box 1)
  - Diet (Box 1)
  - Domestic Hygiene (Box 1)
  - Eye, etc. (Box 1)
  - Eyes, Sleep (Box 1)
  - Hygiene (Box 1)
  - Ligaments (Box 1)
  - Liquor (Box 1)
  - Matters pertaining to Joints, etc (Box 1)
  - Mental Hygiene (Box 1)
  - Muscles (Box 1)
  - Nervous System (Box 1)
  - Public Hygiene (Box 1)
  - Respiration (Box 1)
  - Skin Bathing 1871 (Box 1)
  - Skin, Mucous membranes, Secretion, and Absorption (Box 1)
  - Structure of Teeth (Box 1)
  - Surgical Anatomy (Box 1)
  - Sympathetic Nerve (Box 2)
  - Teeth (Box 2)
  - Tobacco (Box 2)
  - Ventilation (Box 2)
  - Vitality (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous
  The Miscellaneous series is composed of other material maintained by Ford, including record books, correspondence, photographs, and miscellaneous notes. This series also features a letter written by Ford regarding the cane he used most of his life as a result of his childhood paralysis.
  - Anatomical illustrations (Box 2)
  - A Record of Important Cases 1841 (Box 2)
  - Book of Expenses (Box 2)
  - Charts (Box 2)
  - Clothing Exercise Study (Box 2)
  - Correspondence 1883, 1892, undated (Box 2)
  - Invitation to capitol cornerstone laying August 1, 1873 (Box 2)
  - Letter regarding Ford's cane 1884 (Box 2)
  - List of articles belonging to C. L. Ford (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous notes, 1 folder, 3 volumes, and 3 bundles (Box 2)
  - Mutter's Syllabus, 1853 (Box 2)
  - Note paper (Box 2)
  - Photographs (Box 2)
  - Professor Cheever lecture notes (Box 2)
  - Reference posters (Box 2)
  - Report of the faculty activities of C. L. Ford 1875-1877 (Box 2)